Inventory of the Lietuvos TSR Valstybės Saugumo Komitetas [Lithuanian KGB] selected records
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond No. K-23, Records of the Republican Commission of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR for Revision of Criminal Cases of Persons Kept in Camps, Colonies, and Prisons of the SSSR MVD or in Exile in Special Settlements for Counterrevolutionary Crime, 26 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the Republican Commission], 1949-1953; 26 microfilm reels (Reel 1-26)
    Minutes of the Republican Commission. Correspondence with the SSSR Procurator's Office. Statements and statistical surveys concerning revision of cases and rulings on reviewed sentences. Appeal of the LSSR Procurator's Office as an act of supervision. Memorandum from the Commission to the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Lithuania. Cover letters to cases and documents.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 20, Records of the Republican Commission for revision of criminal cases of persons convicted of "counterrevolutionary crimes.")
    Fond K-23, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-23, opis 1 Reel Guide
- Fond No. K-26, Records of the KGB (Committee of State Security) Department under the SSSR Council of Ministers on the Lithuanian Railway, 25 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the Department], 1944-1960; 25 microfilm reels (Reel 488A, 489-511, 1003)
    Reports to the Main Transport Directorate of the SSSR NKGB-KGB. Correspondence with communist party institutions and Soviet authorities. Orders relating to personnel. Directives to NKGB-KGB departments on the Lithuanian Railway, their working plans and accounts. Documents and assets acceptance and transfer statements. Sabotage on the railway cases.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 28, Records of the Department of the SSSR NKGB-MGB-MVD-KGB on the Lithuanian Railway)
    Fond K-26, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-26, opis 1 Reel Guide
- Fond No. K-27, Records of School Number 303 of the Committee of State Security (KGB) under the SSSR Council of Ministers, 12 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the School], 1946-1960; 12 microfilm reels (Reel 27-31, 1004-1010)
    Orders of the director of the Lithuanian school for training operative personnel, school No. 303 of the SSSR NKGB-KGB. Correspondence. Financial documents. Acceptance-transfer statements; materials relating to inspection of existing and destroyed records and discarded documents and written-off assets. Students' grade books.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 29, Records of School No. 303 of the SSSR Committee of State Security (KGB))
    Fond K-27, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-27, opis 1 Reel Guide
    Fond K-27, opis 1 Missing Files List
- Fond No. K-31, Records of the General Service Department of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR, 6 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the General Service Department], 1945-1959; 6 microfilm reels (Reel 271A, 272-276)
    Orders of the NKGB-KGB of the LSSR, its General Service Department, and the Construction Department of the LSSR MGB. Economic and financial papers. Documents relating to financial support rendered to so-called people's defense units. Orders of the LSSR MGB-KGB on job placement of former "people's defense fighters."
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 30, Records of the Construction Department of the NKGB-MGB-MVD-KGB of the LSSR)
    Fond K-31, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-31, opis 1 Reel Guide
- Fond No. K-40, Records of the Investigative Department of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR, 1944–1991; 260 digital files (Reading room workstation)
  The Investigative Department of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR operated under various names in 1940-1941 and 1944-1991. This fond includes files of the First Special Department of the NKVD of the Lithuanian SSR that operated from 1940-1941, the Investigative Department of the NKVD of the Lithuanian SSR that operated from 1944-1953, and the Operative Group of the KGB of the Lithuanian SSR that operated from 1959-1965.
  The department investigated individuals and groups charged with insurgent and anti-Soviet activities. It also investigated criminal cases of special importance, the so-called state prisoners. Beginning in the spring of 1945 the NKVD spent most of its time investigating guerrilla fighters and their accomplices.
  From 1944 to 1953 those charged with anti-Soviet activities were sentenced by extrajudicial institutions (e.g., military tribunals or the Special Council). After 1954 these individuals or their family members were allowed to submit to the KGB of the Lithuanian SSR requests to commute the penalties or annul the sentences imposed on them by the extrajudicial institutions. Thus, beginning in 1955, one responsibility of the Investigative Department was reviewing and revising criminal cases.
  After 1959 KGB and MVD troops liquidated the remnants of the Lithuanian underground. This reduced the number of individuals detained for anti-Soviet crimes and decreased the workload of the Investigative Department.
  The First Division of the Department investigated "traitors of the Motherland," those who helped foreign countries in activities against the Soviet Union and those involved in anti-Soviet agitation, propaganda, and contraband. This division was also responsible for reviewing archived criminal cases.
  Beginning in the 1980s the Second Division investigated criminal cases of espionage, divulgence of military secrets, sedition, violation of rules for currency handling, and economic crimes
  In the 1980s and 1990s heads of divisions investigated the most important cases and took part in reeducating convicted Lithuanian dissidents.
  The activities of the USSR KGB in Lithuania were officially stopped on 22 August 1991 by the resolution of the Supreme Soviet of the Republic of Lithuania. In October-November of the same year the Investigative Department of the Lithuanian SSR was closed down. Access to its documents is limited in accordance with the laws of the Lithuanian Republic.
  Fond no. K-40 also includes materials selected by the Operative Team of the LSSR KGB in 1959-1965. Two retired KGB officers operated as a part of the Editorial Board for Documents Publication of the Institute of History of the Academy of Science of the Lithuanian SSR. The board published archival records held in various archival, governmental, and party institutions that supposedly "exposed anti-public policy of Lithuanian and Polish bourgeois nationalists, evil intents and violence that took place in the bourgeois Lithuania." The documents were used for propaganda by the Communist Party of Lithuania. The two officers, along with staff members of the KGB, searched, selected, arranged, and prepared for publication archival documents about the so-called atrocities of bourgeois nationalists on the territory of the Lithuanian SSR.
  - Opis 1, Files Relating to the Activities of the Department, 1944–1985; 247 digital files
    Files in this opis include working plans, memoranda, and reports prepared by the MGB-KGB of the Lithuanian SSR and subdivisions of the NKVD-MVD of the Lithuanian SSR; the files also contain memoranda regarding investigative activities of the NKVD-KGB institutions; memoranda concerning anti-Soviet activities of individuals or groups; lists of detained persons; criminal proceedings initiated in connection with anti-Soviet activities; interrogation records and witnesses’ testimony records (sometimes copies); correspondence relating to anti-Soviet and other offenses; correspondence concerning rehabilitation of exiled individuals; and records regarding other issues.
    The opis also includes files compiled by the two officers of the Operative Team of the LSSR KGB. They contain memoranda, reports, and correspondence of institutions of the NKGB-KGB of the Lithuanian SSR regarding political figures of pre-war Lithuania, public and political organizations acting in Lithuania during the pre-war and later periods, participants in the 1941 uprising, Lithuanian self-defense battalions, military crimes committed during World War II, Lithuanian guerrilla fighters, and the Polish anti-Soviet underground. The files also contain interrogation and witness testimony records, photographs of individuals charged with anti-Soviet activities, documents (mostly copies) relating to Lithuanian guerrilla fighters and various political organizations (e.g., Union of Nationalists of Lithuania, Geležinis Vilkas, and others), and publications.
    247 files, arranged by the year the file was closed.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 8)
    Fond K-40, opis 1 Content List
  - Opis 2, Files Relating to the Activities of the Department, 1940–1989 (bulk, 1980-1987); 13 digital files
    Opis 2 consists of thirteen files. Two of these files were compiled in 1940-1941 by the First Special Department of the NKVD LSSR and the NKGB Directorate of the Lithuanian SSR in Vilnius. They contain lists of individuals arrested in Lithuania (mostly in Vilnius and Kaunas) in 1940-1941 and interrogated by the NKVD-NKGB, with cover letters. Other files include memoranda on the activities of individuals suspected of war crimes and residing outside the Soviet Union; notes by KGB employees studying at the KGB Higher Educational Institution in Minsk; and evaluations of crime prevention work by the KGB of the Lithuanian SSR.
    Fond K-40, opis 2 Content List
- Fond No. K-42, Records of the Personnel Department of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR, 1941-1990 (bulk, 1963-1988); 98 digital files (Reading room workstation)
  The Personnel Department of the Committee of State Security of the Lithuanian SSR was first established in 1944 as the Personnel Department of the People’s Commissariat of the Lithuanian SSR (NKGB). In 1946 the NKGB became the Ministry of State Security (MGB), and the Personnel Department was renamed accordingly. It should be noted that not many documents relating to the activities of the department from 1944 to 1953 have survived.
  When in 1953 the MGB LSSR was superseded by the Ministry of Internal Affairs (MVD) of the LSSR, its Personnel Department became a structural unit of the MVD. In 1954 the Committee for State Security of LSSR was restored, and its Personnel Department was established. It reported to the USSR KGB Personnel Directorate.
  From 1953 through 1954 it was called the Personnel Department of the Ministry of Internal Affairs (MGB), then from 1954 through 1978, the Personnel Department of the Committee of State Security attached to the Council of Ministers of the Lithuanian SSR. From 1978 through 1991 the Department was called the Personnel Department of the KGB of the Lithuanian SSR
  Activities of the Personnel Department were governed by resolutions and instructions of the USSR KGB and recommendations of the USSR KGB Personnel Directorate. De jure the chief of the Personnel Department had always been Deputy Chair for Cadres of the LSSR KGB while de facto the Personnel Department was run by the deputy chief of the Personnel Department.
  In 1954-1955 the Personnel Department consisted of the following divisions: 1st Division, which organized and managed selection, assignment and education of employees; 2nd Division, or special inspectorate, which investigated crime and misdemeanor committed by employees; 3rd Division, or personnel registration office, which was reorganized into a section for registration of the Personnel Department in May 1955; and 4th Division, which handled mobilization; it was later reorganized into a section for mobilization of the Personnel Departments.
  At the end of the 1960s the Personnel Department started selecting candidates from Lithuania for KGB schools in Moscow, Minsk, Tashkent, and other cities of the USSR and for KGB higher educational institutions in Lithuania, where future KGB employees studied law, foreign languages, journalism, radio electronics, and other subjects.
  From the 1970s through the 1990s one of the responsibilities of the LSSR KGB Personnel Department was distribution of KGB textbooks, curricula, methodological recommendations, etc., supplied by USSR KGB higher educational institutions.
  In the 1980s-1990s the Personnel Department was mainly engaged in: (1) Selecting and hiring personnel of the LSSR KGB. New KGB employees were recruited from large industrial enterprises in Lithuania; (2) Forming reservists for intelligence and counterintelligence subdivisions of the LSSR KGB. Candidates were mostly selected by operative divisions, but the final decision on each candidate was made after a complete background check was conducted by the Personnel Department; (3) Training of operatives and LSSR KGB staff development; (4) Working with young employees; (5) Establishing special training and military and physical education for LSSR KGB personnel. From 1976 seminars were organized in Vilnius, Kaunas, Klaĭpeda, Šiauliaĭ and other cities to train employees of raĭon level divisions of the LSSR KGB; (6) Strengthening discipline and performing ideological education of LSSR KGB employees; (7) Maintaining personnel files of KGB employees; (8) Planning holiday celebrations for personnel.
  The Personnel Department also compiled annual evaluation plans for KGB officers, and managed and analyzed evaluation results. Evaluation was performed in close cooperation with the Committee of the Lithuanian Communist Party at the LSSR KGB.
  In 1974 the Personnel Department established courts of honor at the LSSR KGB. In the second half of the 1980s the Personnel Department started paying special attention to “international education of the KGB cadres.” At the beginning of 1987 there were 14 employees in the Personnel Department.
  On 22 August 1991 the Supreme Soviet (the Seim of the Lithuanian Republic) stopped the activities of the USSR KGB in Lithuania, and in October-November the Personnel Department of the LSS KGB ended its operations.
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the Personnel Department Of the KGB of the Lithuanian SSR], 1962-1988; 60 digital files
    This opis consists of 60 digital PDF files, including correspondence among USSR KGB divisions with KGB divisions in the Lithuanian SSR concerning methodological literature; plans, reports, and informational statements of the LSSR KGB subdivisions regarding work with KGB cadres.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 9)
    Fond K-42, opis 1 Content List
  - Opis 2, Files relating to the activities [of the Personnel Department Of the KGB of the Lithuanian SSR], 1941-1990 (bulk, 1963-1988); 38 digital files
    This opis consists of 38 digital PDF files, including correspondence with KGB divisions concerning work with cadres; documents relating to work of NKVD-NKGB groups involved in gathering intelligence and committing acts of sabotage in Lithuania during the German occupation, 1941-1944; materials relating to education of students at KGB higher educational institutions; and documents concerning NKVD-NKGB officers who perished during the war with Lithuanian guerillas, 1944-1953.
    Fond K-42, opis 2 Content List